Register of the Sergei Nikolaevich Pototskii Papers, 1930-1946
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergei Nikolaevich Pototskii Papers,
1930-1946
47015
Pototskii, Sergei Nikolaevich
40 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 1 envelope (16.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, telegrams, reports, protocols, lists, orders, circulars, accounts, and receipts, card file, and photographs, relating to Russian Imperial military agencies in Copenhagen and Berlin, the Russian Imperial Passport Control Office in Copenhagen, the Russian prisoner-of-war and refugee camp at Horserod, the Russian Red Cross, military benevolent emigre organizations and activities, and Russian participation in World War I and the Russian Civil War.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Rossiiskoe obshchestvo Krasnago kresta.; Russia. Armiia--Officers.; Prisoners of war.; Russians in foreign countries.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1914-1918--Refugees.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Denmark.; Denmark--Foreign relations--Russia.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Russia--Foreign relations--Denmark.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.; Military attaches.
Biographical Note
1877, September 13
(Old Style) Born, St. Petersburg, Russia
1896, August 12 appointed officer, Russian Imperial Army
1896-1921 served in Life Guards, as company and battalion commander, on Staff of Moscow Military District, and on Main Directorate of the General Staff; received Order of St. Vladimir, Third Degree
1911, December 6 promoted to Colonel
1914 appointed acting Military Attache, Denmark
1916 appointed Military Attache, Denmark
1917, September promoted to Major-General
1921 elected to Board of Directors of the Mutual Assistance Association of Russian Officers in Denmark
1922 elected Treasurer of the Mutual Assistance Association of Russian Officers in Denmark
1923, January appointed Delegate of the Russian Red Cross (old organization) in Denmark
1923, October 22 elected to Board of Directors of the Russian Society, Copenhagen
1927, February 18 elected President of the Copenhagen Section of the Association of Russian War Invalids
1927, July joined Copenhagen Charity Fund Committee in Honor of the 80th Birthday of H.I.H. Empress Maria Feodorovna
1929 elected President of the Mutual Assistance Association of Russian Officers in Denmark
Series Description
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN IMPERIAL MILITARY ATTACHÉ, COPENHAGEN, 1903-1944., Boxes 1-14
  Accounts and receipts, correspondence, bulletin Ostinformation (1920), press analyses, press information, and reports, arranged by type of document.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN IMPERIAL MILITARY ATTACHÉ, BERLIN, 1906-1922., Boxes 15-19
  Accounts and receipts, reports, and accounts of the Russian Delegation for Affairs of Prisoners-of-War and Refugees in Germany, arranged by type of document.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE GENERAL MILITARY ASSOCIATION, PARIS, 1919-1939., Box 19
  Circulars, correspondence, financial statements, bulletins, orders, protocols, reports, miscellany, in chronological order.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE ASSOCIATION OF RUSSIAN INVALIDS, 1922-1943., Boxes 20-21
  Accounts, receipts and correspondence, in chronological order.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE MUTUAL ASSISTANCE ASSOCIATION OF RUSSIAN OFFICERS IN DENMARK, 1921-1941., Boxes 21-22
  Accounts and receipts, applications, correspondence, forms, attendance lists, protocols, and other material, arranged by type of document.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE COMMITTEE FOR THE COLLECTION OF A CHARITY FUND IN HONOR OF THE 80th BIRTHDAY OF HER IMPERIAL HIGHNESS EMPRESS MARIA FEODOROVNA, 1927-1929., Boxes 22-25
  Accounts and receipts, circular letters, correspondence, lists of donors, lists of petitions for aid, newspaper issues, protocols, arranged by type of document.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN PRISONER-OF-WAR CAMP AT HORSERØD DENMARK, 1917-1920., Boxes 26-28
  Accounts and receipts, correspondence, lists of donors, orders, arranged by type of document.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN IMPERIAL PASSPORT CONTROL OFFICE, COPENHAGEN, 1917-1920., Boxes 28-33
  Accounts and receipts, correspondence, reports, and card file.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN RED CROSS IN DENMARK, 1919-1946., Boxes 34-35
  Accounts and receipts and correspondence in chronological order.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1915-1946., Boxes 35-39
  Accounts and receipts, charts, circulars, clippings, correspondence, declarations, lists, protocols, reports, and other materials, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1903-1946., Box 40
  Arranged by subseries (letters sent and letters received) and thereunder alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE.
  See photo file.
Container List
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN IMPERIAL MILITARY ATTACHÉ, COPEHHAGEN, 1903-1947
  - Accounts and Receipts (Box 1)
    - Accounts
      - 1914-1917
      - 1914-1919
      - 1917-1920
      - 1918-1922
      - 1919 (Box 2)
      - November, 1919
      - December, 1919
      - January, 1920
      - February, 1920
      - March, 1920
      - April, 1920
      - 1920
    - Bank Statements, 1921-1924 (Box 3)
    - Checks, 1921
    - Invoices
    - Receipts, 1926-1940
    - Vouchers
      - 1918
      - 1919
    - Miscellaneous
  - General Correspondence
    - 1903-1917
    - 1918-1919 (Box 4)
    - 1919-1920
    - 1919-1927
    - 1919-1937
  - Letters received (Box 5)
    - 1915-1916
    - 1916-1917
    - 1916-1929
    - 1917-1918
    - 1918-1919
    - 1919 (Box 6)
    - 1920
    - 1926-1930
    - 1927-1942
    - 1930-1943
    - 1933-1941
  - Letters sent (Box 7)
    - 1915
    - 1917
    - 1917-1918 (Box 8)
    - 1925-1928
    - 1928-1931
    - 1931
    - 1932-1937 (Box 9)
    - 1934
    - 1938-1944
  - Telegrams
    - Incoming
      - 1916-1917
      - 1916-1918 (Box 10)
    - Outgoing, 1919-1920
    - Miscellaneous telegrams
  - Miscellaneous correspondence
  - Ostinformation (Bulletin) (formerly Russischer Bericht, No. 18-26), 1920
    - No. 18-26
    - No. 27-36
    - No. 37-44
    - No. 46-58 (Box 11)
    - No. 62-77
  - Press Analyses
  - Press Information, 1919-1920
  - Registers, military (Box 12)
    - Officer's ranks, 1917-1922
    - Servicemen, 1920
  - Reports, economic, military and political
    - 1917 (Bulgarian army)
    - 1917 (German infantry)
    - 1917 (Military charts)
    - 1917-1918 (Military reports)
    - 1918 (Economic and military reports)
    - 1919-1920 (Military and political reports) (Box 13)
    - 1920 (Military and political reports)
    - 1921 (Various) (Box 14)
  - Clippings and telegrams from Vestnik, 1917
  - Newspaper issues, brochures, clippings, printed material
  - Announcements
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN IMPERIAL MILITARY ATTACHÉ, BERLIN, 1906-1922
  - Accounts and receipts (Box 15)
    - Accounts
      - September 1921
      - October 1921
      - November 1921
      - December 1921
      - January 1922
      - February 1922
    - Receipts, 1918
  - Reports, military-political and military-historical, 1906-1914 (Box 16)
    - America, South
    - Austria-Hungary
    - Belgium and Holland
    - Bulgaria
    - Denmark
    - England
    - France
    - Germany
    - Italy
    - Japan and China
    - Revolutionaries, Arms for
    - Romania
    - Socialism
    - Sweden and Norway
    - Switzerland
    - Turkey and Afghanistan
  - Publication, entitled Die Entwickelung der Sozial-Demokratie und ihr Einfluss auf das Deutsche Heer
  - Russian Delegation for Affairs of Prisoners-of-War and Refugees in Germany, Accounts and Receipts
    - May, 1920
      - Sums received from the Northwest Army
      - Sums received from the Paris military representation
    - June, 1920
      - Sums received from the Northwest Army
      - Sums received from the Paris military representation
    - July, 1920 (Box 17)
      - Sums received from the Northwest Army
      - Sums received from the Volunteer Army
    - August, 1920
    - September, 1920
    - October, 1920
    - November, 1920 (Box 18)
    - December, 1920
    - January, 1921
    - February, 1921
    - March, 1921
    - April, 1921 (Box 19)
    - May, 1921
    - June, 1921
    - July, 1921
    - August, 1921
- OFFICE FILE OF THE GENERAL MILITARY ASSOCIATION, 1919-1939
  - Circulars, 1925-1939 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1937
  - Financial Statements, 1935-1936
  - Information Bulletins, 1930-1937
  - Orders, 1919-1939
  - Plan and Constitution
  - Protocols, 1936-1937
  - Reports, 1926-1928
  - Miscellaneous
- OFFICE FILE OF THE ASSOCIATION OF RUSSIAN INVALIDS, 1922-1943
  - Accounts, receipts and letters, 1923-1924 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1922-1931
      - 1931-1943
    - Letters sent, 1927-1928
  - Vouchers, 1929-1943 (Box 21)
- OFFICE FILE OF THE MUTUAL ASSISTANCE ASSOCIATION OF RUSSIAN OFFICERS IN DENMARK, 1921-1941
  - Accounts and receipts, 1921-1938 (Box 21)
    - Annual financial reports, 1921-1930
    - Ledger, 1921-1926
    - Vouchers, 1928-1938
  - Applications for entering the Association
  - Correspondence, 1921-1940
    - 1921-1935, Letters received
    - 1921-1937, Letters sent
    - 1924-1940 (Post-telegrams)
  - Enquiry forms (Box 22)
  - Lists of attendance and voting, general meetings
  - Loan, grant-in-aid and collection records
  - Protocols
    - Directors' meetings, 1921-1925
    - Directors' meetings, 1925-1938
    - General meetings, 1921-1924
    - General meetings, 1925-1940
  - Various, 1921-1941
- OFFICE FILE OF THE COMMITTEE FOR THE COLLECTION OF A CHARITY FUND IN HONOR OF THE 80TH BIRTHDAY OF HER IMPERIAL HIGHNESS EMPRESS MARIA FEODOROVNA, 1927-1929
  - Accounts and Receipts (Box 22)
    - Account book, 1927-1928
    - Bank receipts, 1928 (Box 23)
    - General financial chart
    - Postal receipt book, 1928-1929
    - Miscellaneous
  - Circular Letters
  - Correspondence, 1927-1929
    - Alphabetical file
      - A-L
      - M-Z (Box 24)
    - Chronological file
      - 1927
      - 1928
      - 1929
      - Undated
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 25)
  - Lists of Donors
  - Lists of Petitions for Aid
    - Chronological file, February-November, 1928
    - Geographical file
  - Newspaper Issues
  - Protocols
    - Committee sessions, 1927 (fund collection)
    - Committee sessions, 1928 (fund distribution)
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN PRISONER-OF-WAR CAMP AT HORSERØD, DENMARK, 1917-1920
  - Accounts and Receipts (Box 26)
    - General accounts
    - General chronological file, 1917
    - Bank account
    - Bicycles, funds for
    - Church, building of
    - Evacuation
    - Funerals, funds for (Box 27)
    - Journal of finances, Delegation of the War Ministry, Horserød
    - Ledger, Treasury of War Ministry for Internee Affairs, Horserød
    - Matériel, funds for
    - Military agent, funds from
    - Prosthetic appliances, funds for
  - Correspondence, 1917-1919
    - General, 1917-1919
    - Financial, 1918-1919 (Box 28)
  - Orders (Drafts)
  - Miscellany
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN IMPERIAL PASSPORT CONTROL OFFICE, COPENHAGEN, 1917-1920
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1917-1920 (Box 28)
    - 1917-1919
    - 1919-1920
  - Correspondence, 1917-1920
    - 1917-1919
    - 1919
    - 1919-1920
  - Reports
    - Baum, Leo and MOSKET (Moscow Aid Committee for Prisoners-of-War)
    - Germany
      - Bolsheviks and
      - Persons traveling to
    - Intelligence reports
    - Letters intercepted, etc.
    - Loevskii, A. K., affair
    - Ukrainian mission in Copenhagen
  - Card file (Box 29-33)
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN RED CROSS IN DENMARK, 1919-1946
  - Accounts and Receipts (Box 34)
    - Accounts, 1923-1932
    - Accounts, 1933-1943; accounts of the Association of Russian Military Invalids, 1933-1938
    - Receipts, vouchers, etc., 1929-1942
  - Correspondence, 1919-1946
    - Letters received
      - 1919-1925
      - 1925-1946
    - Letters sent
      - 1919-1922
      - 1923-1924
      - 1925-1926
    - 1936 (Box 35)
    - 1937-1944
- SUBJECT FILE, 1915-1946
  - Berlin, Russian military organizations in (Box 35)
  - Comintern
  - Courts of honor, military
  - Escapees from German capativity, correspondence and lists
  - Evacuation of soldiers, Northern Front
  - Hornbaek, monument at
    - Committee for
    - Correspondence regarding
    - Lists of donors
    - List of soldiers deceased
    - Various
  - Horserød, internees at (Box 36)
  - International Anti-Communist League (International League against the Third International)
  - Inventions, correspondence regarding
  - League of Nations, report of Hanson before, May 11, 1937
  - Military schools, Paris
  - Naval officers, Russian
    - Correspondence, 1927-1931
    - Correspondence, 1931-1940 (Box 37)
  - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke
    - Declarations
    - Fund committee
  - Northwest Army
  - Officers, Russian
    - General, 1919-1926
    - Correspondence, 1918-1919
    - Correspondence, 1918-1941 (Box 38)
  - Officers' Associations, Council of United Russian, Belgrade
    - General
    - Correspondence
  - Personnel, Military Agency, Copenhagen
  - Prisoners-of-war and refugees
    - Inquiries of captive officers
    - Miscellany
  - Refugees, Russian
    - Inquiries concerning
    - Visas for
  - Russian Charity Association, Labor Division
    - Accounts, receipts, vouchers, etc., 1925-1934
    - Cash-book, 1925-1929
    - Cash-book, 1930-1937
  - Russian Society, Copenhagen
    - Accounts and receipts
      - Annual accounts, 1920-1928
      - Ledger and address book, 1919-1926
    - Guest book, 1925-1929 (Box 39)
    - Protocols of meetings, 1919-1924
    - Various
  - Schleswig, Russian graves in
  - U.S.S.R. trade delegation to Denmark
  - Wrangel, General Petr' Nikolaevich, Declaration of Young Men's Christian Association, correspondence, 1918-1920
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1921-1946
  - Letters received (Box 40)
    - Adamovich, Ivan N.
    - Al'tenburgskaia, Princess Elena G.
    - Arkhangel'skii, General A.P.
    - Ballovut, L.
    - Bane, Karl
    - Banner-Fogt, Colonel Oleg G.
    - Bazarevich, Vladimir I.
    - Bezobrazov, Lieutenant-Colonel Mikhail V.
    - Brunner, Colonel Nikolai N.
    - Cadet Corps, First Russian, Director
    - Dekhterev, A.
    - Des Fontaines, Edward E.
    - Elchaninov, V.
    - Elizarov, V.
    - Evgeniev, M.
    - Fogel', Major-General Nikolai F.
    - Friends of National Russia, Society of
    - Gedroits, Prince Nikolai Ts.
    - Ger, N.
    - Gokkane, Aleksandra N.
    - Goncharenko, Major General Iurii I.
    - Grabar, Andrei
    - Grabar, Petr'
    - Gravesen, N. S.
    - Grigor'ev, Colonel Artemii F.
    - Guchkov, A. I.
    - Gunco, Anna
    - Héroys, Boris V.
    - Ianchshevskii, Grigorii E.
    - Iankov, P.
    - Iankova, V.
    - Inquiry Office, Main, Constantinople
    - Invalids, Association of Russian War, Kingdom of Yugoslavia
    - Ioann (monk)
    - Iskoldoff, Eugen
    - Kamenev, M.
    - Karrik, Valerii V.
    - Kolchev, Father Leonid
    - Korval' (Corval), Iurii Peze de
    - Kostevich (Kostevitch), M.M.
    - Kotliarevskii, Aleksandr
    - Kotliarevskii, Petri A.
    - Kovalevskaia, E.
    - Krylov, Staff Captain Boris P.
    - Lampe, Major General Aleksei A. von
    - Lekhovich, Lieutenant General V.
    - Lieven, Prince Anatole
    - Linder, Kitty
    - Lodyzhenskii, Iurii I.
    - Loevskii, A. K.
    - Marfo-Mariinskoe Chapel, Berlin
    - Mecklenburg, Georgii, Duke of
    - Miller, General Evgenii K.
    - Nansen International Office for Refugees, President
    - Nikol'skii, Major General Vladimir P.
    - Paleologue, Sergei N. (Commissar General for the organization of Russian refugees in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes)
    - Panasenko, Sava (Panassenko, Sawa)
    - Pliutsinskii, Colonel Boris A.
    - Popovskii, Colonel (first name unknown)
    - Prokofiev, Nikolai N.
    - Pylkin, V.
    - Rubets, Father Aleksandr
    - Sablin (Sabline), E.
    - Saburov, Vladimir
    - Sadovskii, P.
    - Shal'burg, Lieutenant Konstantin F.
    - Shenk, Colonel Vladimir K.
    - Shtrandtmann, Vasilii N.
    - Shtubendorf, Major General Aleksei O.
    - Shuvalova, A.
    - Siial'skii, Colonel Vladimir P.
    - Smirnov, S.
    - Suvinskii, B.
    - Tranze, Aleksandr A. von
    - Tsvetkov, N.
    - Tyrin, Andrei S.
    - Vasko, Grigorii
    - Voronkova, Ol'ga
    - Zaitsev, Arsenii A.
    - Zinkevich, M.
    - Miscellaneous
  - Letters sent
    - Ekk, E. V.
    - Military Agent in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes
    - Nielsen, General (first name unknown)
    - Scavenius, Harald
    - Shtrandtman, Vasilii N.
    - Uget, Sergei A.